Sicario Day of the Soldado, or just
simply Soldado, is a very different film
to its predecessor Sicario. Both films
deal with themes of institutional
corruption and the cyclical nature of
violence,
but there's a fundamental difference
between the two, and that's in how they
position us as the audience within their
[music] narratives. It changes
everything, especially when it comes to
how effectively each film's core ideas
and messages actually land. And it
starts with Kate
Experiencing the story through Kate
[music] makes Sicario what it is,
particularly during the quieter moments
of the film, such as the boardroom
scene, [music] the briefing scene, the
bus station scene. These sequences
aren't just visually [music]
fascinating, they're restrained in their
storytelling, and that restraint forces
us to become active participants [music]
as opposed to passive viewers.
Compositions take care to frame Kate in
ways that keep her isolated [music] and
alienated. Dialogue is minimal, cryptic,
and withholds the truth.
>> Where is he?
Uh he's in the
El Paso [music] area. It's these writing
and filmmaking choices that establish
the film's conflict, hierarchy, and
crucially, mystery. Okay.
And elevates Sicario into a far more
compelling piece of cinema. During the
boardroom scene, for instance, not only
are we made to feel Kate's isolation and
powerlessness in the dialogue, Am I
married?
Am I married? cinematography [music] and
blocking, we leave the scene asking the
same questions as her. Who is Matt
Graver? Is anything he says true?
What is Kate really [music] getting
herself into here? Think very hard
before you respond. Some questions are
answered, but like Kate, we're left
needing more. And that's the mark of
good, layered, immersive storytelling.
And the result is that through Kate,
Sicario forces us to inhabit
uncertainty, narratively, legally, and
morally. Kate's perspective grounds us
[music] in what is legal, which allows
us to recognize just how far Graver and
his team are operating outside of it.
And it's this that opens the door
[music] for us to question whether these
actions are moral or even effective.
>> that was [__] illegal. You want to
start a war? You're a [__] spook.
>> The film doesn't pass judgement. It
presents a system where morality,
legality, and necessity are constantly
at odds. You getting the vibe that we're
winning?
No.
And leaves us to reconcile that
ourselves, which is why there are so
many ways to interpret Sicario's
narrative and what it's trying to say.
Even the cartel isn't reduced to
something purely monstrous. Villeneuve
deliberately humanizes its characters,
[music] giving just enough dimension to
complicate our response to them. We see
this with Silvio, where the glimpses of
his quiet family life and this line,
And what do you want to do?
turn this moment
from a generic action beat into a
continuation of the film's core themes.
We see it in the determined resistance
[music] of the cartel members at the
border crossing, raising arms in a
moment of utter one-sided hopelessness,
giving the moment more nuance rather
than reducing it to [music] pure
villainy. And of course, we see it with
Fausto Alarcón, the cartel executioner
responsible for Alejandro's
transformation from law-abiding family
man to ruthless Sicario, whom we only
ever get to know as a caring father and
husband.
I don't want to hurt my boys.
It's this moral tension in Sicario that
makes it such a powerful picture of
moral [music] and legal ambiguity. It
doesn't tell us what to think so much as
it constructs a moral framework that
forces us to decide. And that is where
Soldado changes things. It removes that
framework, and in doing so, strips away
the uncertainty, and with it, the need
for us to think at all. What we end up
with isn't just a different story, it's
a fundamentally different experience.
Soldado presents its story's core
corruption at face value. You want to
see this thing through?
I'm going to have to get
dirty. And trades moral tension for
spectacle.
But it's the moral tension that gives
the violence in Sicario its weight.
What the [__] are we doing?
Every act of violence is contextualized,
given perspective, consequence, and
reaction, so that we're not just
witnessing them, we're morally
positioned to confront them.
In Soldado, that context is largely
absent. Violence is presented more
directly, without the same emphasis on
consequence, reaction, or moral
ambiguity. We see it in the opening
bombing, where the deaths of a mother
and child are used to establish stakes,
but without the same emotional or
narrative grounding that we would have
had in Sicario. We see it in Alejandro's
execution of this nameless guy, which is
played less as a moral turning point
accented by reaction shots and genuine
emotion and consequence, but instead as
a simple continuation of his mythos and
ruthlessness.
And we see it in the helicopter rescue
towards the end, where the violence is
one-sided and the cartel members aren't
given anywhere near the same humanistic
treatment as they are in Sicario, where
their actions, even though
unquestionably grim, are balanced with
moments that complicate our perspective.
In Soldado, by contrast, they're
depicted one-dimensionally as purely
evil with very little nuance or
redeemable qualities. So, here, even as
the helicopters close in, we're never
permitted to feel their fear or
desperation, something that could have
brought a new dimension to both them and
the sequence as a whole. Instead, the
sequence is framed mostly from a
distance, and brutality takes the
spotlight, stripping the moment of the
ambiguity and emotion that made similar
ones in Sicario so unsettling and
morally complicated. And the result is
that Soldado gives us something simpler,
clearer, and ultimately far less
impactful. And this isn't just a
narrative difference, it's embedded in
the filmmaking itself. Have a closer
look at how each film handles its
interrogation scene. In Soldado, it's a
very simple scene in terms of its
blocking, camera work, and other
compositional choices. There isn't
nearly as much storytelling embedded
within the images themselves compared to
Sicario. It's mostly constructed in a
shot-reverse-shot style in very dark,
moody lighting. Other than this shot of
Graver's Crocs, which functions as both
a nice callback to his flip-flops in
Sicario and a reinforcement of his
nonchalant, relaxed demeanor, the
cinematography does little to extend the
meaning of the scene beyond what's being
said.
No rules today, sport. In Sicario,
things are very different. The scene is
not only briefer, but it's punctuated by
some seriously impressive visual
storytelling. The water jug,
forcing choosing to leave the room, I'm
going to step out.
his decision to switch the camera off on
his way out,
and this slow zoom descending towards
the drain pipe. We're shown that
something illegal is about to take place
instead of being told. And by letting
the images do the heavy lifting, it
gives more weight to the atmosphere and
forces us to sit in the silence and feel
the tension in the room far more
effectively. And this lean, intentional
visual storytelling runs throughout the
scene. Similar to shots all throughout
Sicario, Villeneuve and his
cinematographer, the legendary Roger
Deakins, use every dimension of the
frame to tell their story. Along the Y
axis, blocking reinforces power
dynamics, reminding us who holds
control, and combined with shots like
this, how far we're descending into the
illegal.
To be fair, Soldado does use a similar
framing at one point, but here, the
proximity to the camera, the low angle,
and the cramped framing of Guillermo
make the claustrophobia and power
imbalance far more tangible. Along the Z
axis, Villeneuve and Deakins use depth
to keep the focus where it matters.
Forcing switching off the camera becomes
a subtle background beat rather than an
entirely separate shot, which it could
easily have been. It's an important
detail for communicating the scene's
illicit nature, but Villeneuve and
Deakins don't pull us away to show it.
They keep us with Alejandro because he's
the dominant force in the room. It's his
presence and intensity that drive the
emotion and story of the scene, so
that's where they keep us. And yet, they
still find a way to include other
details like this that make the scene
whole. We see something similar in the
framing here, where Graver is removed to
the background, fully aware, but also
relaxed and detached. And it's shots
like this that quietly tell the full
story in Sicario, the power of Graver
and his operation, how relaxed he and
his men are with what they're doing, and
how much humanity they're willing to
sacrifice to get the job done. None of
these filmmaking decisions are flashy or
over the top, but together, they give
this moment a greater dimension, a sense
of intimacy, weight, and atmosphere that
elevate this interrogation sequence into
something far beyond what's happening on
the surface. And above all, through what
happens in this room and what happens
before it,
What the [__] are we doing? These
decisions force us to confront the key
question the film keeps asking but never
explicitly answers. Are these men
actually the good guys.
That's what's missing in Soldado scene.
It doesn't hinge on involving us as the
audience and using the scene to hint at
the film's deeper themes of corruption.
There's no implicit sense of illegality
being conveyed through the images. No
camera being turned off, no atmospheric
build-up or sense of impending dread.
We're not forced to imagine the
violence, which always makes it worse.
Instead, it's explicit. We're told
exactly which side of the line Graver
stands on. This is Africa.
I can do whatever the [__] I want here.
And the entire scene hinges on an act of
violence. An act that's presented in a
very different way to how it was handled
at the end of Sicario. A scene also
involving a defenseless but clearly bad
person being forced to sit through the
death of his family. Here though, the
moment is underpinned by pure emotion
from both sides of the table. And we're
not shown the result of the scene's
violence until well after we've been
forced to feel its impact. Even knowing
what this man has done to Alejandro, it
makes the moment feel visceral and
morally complex. In Soldado, we witness
this man's loss, but it feels
impersonal. There's no build-up, no
connection to the family, and all we get
of his reaction is this.
It's not ineffective, but it lacks the
emotional weight of seeing that reaction
play out on his face. Consequently,
there's almost no emotional or moral
investment on our side. And that pretty
much sums up Soldado. It just doesn't
engage with the same legal and moral
dimensions that Sicario does. And it's a
far shallower experience for [music] it.
Lines like this,
Dirty is exactly why you're here.
Are the sort of lines that sound cool,
but they don't really carry anything
with them beyond their one single
utterance. [music] They don't add
anything to the story other than style.
And style isn't what made Sicario great.
Put another way, when Denis Villeneuve's
favorite scene from Sicario is this one,
>> They would be beyond law and and and and
they will do something that is illegal.
[music] And this is one that I thought
was pretty cinematic. And Roger Deakins'
favorite sequence [music] is this one,
You know, for me the strongest scene in
the whole of Sicario is at the end in
the kitchen where it's just Benicio and
Emily. Largely because of how much
meaning and thematic complexity they
bring to the film, it really does seem
like the team behind Soldado missed
something when they chose to steer their
film in the direction of action set
pieces and pure spectacle. And that's
really the key difference. Sicario's
power doesn't come from its violence.
[music] It comes from the moments around
it. The conversations, the silences, the
uncertainty,
the details that force us to sit with
what the film is really saying. The
violence is simply a release. And even
then, it's framed in a way with
something meaningful [music] to say. In
Soldado, those moments are largely
absent. When things slow down, it feels
more like a bridge between set pieces
[music] than true substance. Still, to
be fair, it does occasionally gesture
towards this. Alejandro's interaction
with the deaf man, for instance, hints
at a more introspective character-driven
approach that does succeed in slowing
things down and briefly reconnecting us
with something more human. But moments
like this are the exception, not the
foundation in Soldado. And without that
foundation, [music] they simply don't
carry the same weight. Because Sicario
doesn't just depict a world of moral
compromise, [music] it makes you feel
what it's like to live in one. Yes, it
has its moments of violence, [music] but
it gives the violence a reason for being
there. It gives it the genuine moral
weight it deserves, positioning it
[music] in a way that reinforces the
story's exploration of morality,
illegality, and ultimately what it means
to not just exist in the land of wolves,
but survive there, too.
And that's what Soldado loses. It
escalates the violence, but it abandons
the perspective, the complexity, and the
emotion-driven filmmaking decisions that
gave that violence weight and meaning.
And in doing so, it misses the point.
But hopefully, if they do go ahead with
this third installment [music] there's
been talk of, they'll remember exactly
what it was that made Sicario such a
powerful and special story.
Thank you very much for watching.